Philip M. Sheppard Papers 1911-1976 1940-1976 Mss.Ms.Coll.65
American Philosophical Society
- Series I. Correspondence, 1946-1983; 28 boxes, 14 lin. feet
  - Wright, Ann, 1969 (Box Series I-28)
  - Wright, C. A., 1964; 1973-75 (Box Series I-28)
  - Wright, Clive J., 1969 (Box Series I-28)
  - Wright, J. W., 1966-69 (Box Series I-28)
    Southwood, T.R.E.
  - Wulff, Daniel L., 1975 (Box Series I-28)
  - Wyatt, H. V., 1972; 1975 (Box Series I-28)
  - Wynne, Goronwy, 1962-68 (Box Series I-28)
  - Wynne-Davies, Ruth (Box Series I-28)
  - Yamaguchi, Akio, 1969 (Box Series I-28)
  - Yang, Ying-Leh, 1961 (Box Series I-28)
  - Yannopoulos, George, 1973 (Box Series I-28)
  - Yeung, Kai K., 1968 (Box Series I-28)
  - Yonge, Maurice, 1968 (Box Series I-28)
  - Yorkshire Television Ltd., 1974-75 (Box Series I-28)
  - Young, A., 1968 (Box Series I-28)
  - Young, Bryan, 1950-51 (Box Series I-28)
  - Young, C. S. H, 1966 (Box Series I-28)
  - Young, D. P., 1964 (Box Series I-28)
  - Young, J. O., 1968 (Box Series I-28)
  - Young, J. Z., 1963; 1974 (Box Series I-28)
  - Youngs, Brian K., 1968 (Box Series I-28)
  - Yu, Ching-Jin, 1961 (Box Series I-28)
  - Zawahri, Mokhtar M., 1968 (Box Series I-28)
  - Zehetmayr, Susan, 1973 (Box Series I-28)
  - Zeuner, F. E. (Box Series I-28)
  - Ziman, John M., 1974 (Box Series I-28)
  - Zimmerman, David R., 1969; 1973 (Box Series I-28)
    Levene, Howard
  - Zipursky, A. (Box Series I-28)
  - Zohary, Daniel, 1970 (Box Series I-28)
  - Zoological Society, 1955-56; 1971 (Box Series I-28)
- Series II. Subject files, 1952-1976; 2 boxes, 1.0 lin. foot (Box Series II Boxes 1-2)
  Minutes, agenda, reports, newsletters, and reviews. The series also contains drafts and outlines of papers and lectures given by Sheppard. The folders are arranged alphabetically by title with the form of the item noted when appropriate. The earliest item in the series is a 1952 outline of his paper "Polymorphism and Population Studies." Other early items in the series are drafts of his papers on ABO blood groups, and outlines for lectures at the University of Liverpool. The subjects covered in this series include mimicry and polymorphism in Cepaea nemoralis, Heliconius, and Papilio, blood groups, and thyroid disease. Of possible interest are some preliminary notes and outlines on the book Practical Genetics, which he edited.
  Bibliographical matters; Biographical and personal data; Cancer, chemotherapy; Drosophila genetics; Editorial matters; Genetics -- Birds; Genetics -- Butterflies, moths; Genetics -- Snails; Human genetics; Human genetics -- Blood groups; Lectures, public speaking -- University of Liverpool; Population genetics; Publication -- Practical Genetics; Radiation genetics; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
  - [The ABO Blood Groups and Secretor Character in Duodenal Ulcer], [1956?]
    Review
  - The ABO Blood Groups and Secretor Character in Duodenal Ulcer, [1956?]
    Draft
  - Absence of Crossing-Over in Female Butterlies (Heliconius), 1975
    -See Ser.I, Turner, John R.G.
  - Background Genetics-Human Biology
    Lecture Outline?
  - Bauer, H., n.d.
    Notes on method
  - "The Induction of Polyploidy by Cold Treatment in Drosophila melanogaster" (1946)
  - Biographical Information, 1956; 1965
  - [Blood Groups], n.d.
    Notes
  - Blood Groups and Disease, 1957
    Draft letter
  - Blood Groups and Disease
    Lecture Outline
  - Blood Groups and Natural Selection, [1958?]
  - Blood Groups and Secretor Status of Students in Dept. [of] Zoology
  - Brazil-Visiting Professorship, 1972; n.d.
  - [Broom], n.d.
  - Butterflies-Shipping & Egg-Laying, n.d.
  - Carcinoma of the Oesophagus in a Family with Keratosis Palmaris et Plantaris (Tylosis), [1958?]
  - Chester, n.d.
  - Committee of the Vice-Chancellors and Principals of the Universities of the United Kingdom, 1967; 1970
  - Conference Programs, 1970; 1972
  - Contribution to the Effective Population Size of the Variance in the Numbers of Eggs Produced Per Individual, [1959?]
    -See Ser.III, Panaxia dominula #4
  - [Contributions to Effective Population Size in dominula]
  - Cuckoos' Eggs and Mimicry, [1954?]
  - Development of Biology Within the University, n.d.
  - Drosophila Food, n.d.
  - [Drosophila Stocks], 1964
  - Ecological Genetics and the Evolution Under Domestication
  - "Etheocles" Families, n.d.
    Notes may be by V.G.L. VanSomeren
  - Evolution of Batesian Mimicry, n.d.
    Lecture Notes
  - Existence of Muellerian Mimicry, 1976
  - Experimental Studies on Microevolution in Populations of the Lepidoptera, 1964
  - An Experimental Study of the Dwarf Broom (Cytisus scoparius spp. prostratus), 1958
  - Experiments on "Preferences" for certain cereals in hens, n.d.
  - F. carbonaria Distribution on British Isles, n.d.
  - "Freak Cockerel" [Mating Data], n.d.
  - [Gene Linkage], n.d.
    Outline
  - Genetic Control of the Melanic Form of insularia of the moth Biston betularia (L)., [1964]
  - A Genetic Inves[tigation] of Mimicry, [1958]
    -See also Ser.II, The Genetics of Some
    Forms of Papilio dardanus, Brown, and Papilio glaucus, Linn.
  - Genetic Variability and Polymorphism: Synthesis, [1956]
    Proofs
  - [Genetics Course Lectures], [1958?-59]
    Outlines
    -See also Ser.II, Hazards of Atomic Radiation (Cp. Lecture #8)
  - Genetics for Vet[erinarian]s, n.d.
  - The Genetics of Four New Forms of the Mimetic Butterfly Papilio memnon L., 1973
    -See Ser.I, Royal Society
  - The Genetics of Papilio dardanus Brown, [195?]
    Draft ms.
  - The Genetics of Some Mimetic Forms of Papilio dardanus, Brown, and Papilio glaucus, Linn., [195?]
  - Geology Talk, n.d.
  - Group Variation and Polymorphism
  - Hardy, G.H., n.d.
  - "Mendelian Proportions in a Mixed Group Population" [1908]
  - Hazards of Atomic Radiation, n.d.
    -See also Ser.II, [Genetics Course Lectures], Lecture #8
  - [Hemolytic Disease of the Newborn], n.d.
  - Historical Aspects [of Genetics], n.d.
  - Human Genetics, n.d.
  - Institute for Research Into Mental Retardation. Annual Report, 1973
  - [Introductory Lecture], n.d.
  - Invitations, 1974; n.d.
  - John Innes Symposium, Second, 1973
  - Lecture, 2 Oct.
  - Lecture [Chester 3], n.d.
  - Lecture notes [miscellaneous], n.d.
  - Lecture Notices and Schedules, 1968-76; n.d.
  - Lep[idoptera] News, 1956
    abstract
  - "Linkage and the Blood Groups", 1954
    Draft, comments
  - American Journal of Human Genetics
  - Liverpool Medical Institution, 1967
  - Merseyside Biology Teachers' Bulletin
    -See Ser.I, University of Liverpool. Institute of Education. Science Teachers' Centre
  - Mimicry, 1965
    Draft script
    -See Ser.I, British Broadcasting Corporation
  - [Mimicry], n.d.
  - Mimicry and Its Ecological Aspects, [196?]
  - Miscellanea, n.d.
  - [Mosquito Hybridization], [195?]
  - Natural Environment Research Council. Genetics of Fish & Shellfish, 1972
    -See also Ser.I, Natural Environment Research Council
  - [Natural Selection in Cepaea], [1954?]
    Comments
  - Northern Universities Working Party for Cooperation in Education Technology. Biology Newsletter, 1974
  - Packing of living material, n.d.
  - Polymorphism, n.d.
    Lecture outline, draft
  - Polymorphism & Population Studies, [1952?]
    -See Ser.III, Research Notebook #11
  - [Polymorphism in Panaxia dominula & Cepaea nemoralis], 1956
    -See Ser.III, Research Notebook #21
  - Polyploidy and Its Role in Adaptation to Unfavourable Conditions, 1957
  - Practical Genetics, [1966-71]
    Notes, outlines
  - Prevention of Rh Haemolytic Disease, [1964]
    Letter
  - Professor Lewis' Review of Variation and Heredity from 3rd Programme
  - Proposed Course in Genetics for 1st B.V.Sc. Students, n.d.
  - Proposed Investigations, n.d.
  - Protective Coloration in Some British Moths, [1963?]
  - [Public Health lectures], n.d.
  - Publications and Reviews list, [1956; 1964]
  - Quaternary Refugia in Tropical America: Evidence from Race Formation in Heliconius Butterflies, 1974
    -See Ser.I, Royal Society (1974)
    -See Ser.I, Turner, John R.G. (1974)
  - Queensland Trip [Brood Numbers and Locations], 1967
  - [Rare Genes], n.d.
    lecture outline
  - Reading list [for Genetics course?], n.d.
  - Reference, n.d.
  - The Relative Importance of Natural Selection and "Genetic Drift" in Evolution
    table of contents
  - Research Talk, n.d.
    outline
  - [Reviews by Sheppard], [1958]-1968; n.d.
  - Royal Society. Aldabra Newsletter, 1970-73
  - Royal Society. Aldabra Research Committee. Minutes, 1969-73
    -See also Ser.I, Royal Society. Aldabra Research Committee
  - The Secretion of Blood Group Antigens in Peptic Ulcer, 1958
  - The Secretion of the ABH Antigens in Peptic Ulcer, 1958
    -See Ser.II, Secretion of Blood Group Antigens in Peptic Ulcer
  - [Selection], n.d.
  - Semi-Albino a Third Sex-Linked Allelomorph of Silver and Gold in the Fowl, [1959?]
    draft
  - Simplified Sketch of Four Year Fluctuation in Numbers of Voles [by "D.H.C."], 1958
  - The Study of Populations of Lepidoptera by Capture-Recapture Methods, 1973
    Draft. -See Ser.I, Hovanitz, William
  - Symposium on Variation in Mammalian Populations, 1969
  - [Thesis comments], n.d.
  - Thyroid Disease and the P.T.C. Taste Response, 1958
  - Types of Selection, n.d.
  - United States. Dept. of Agriculture. Animal and Plant Health Inspection Service. Plant Protection and Quarantine Programs, 1975
  - University of Cambridge. Dept. of Genetics. Report, [1967]
  - [University of Liverpool. Dept. of Genetics], n.d.
    draft report
  - University of Liverpool. Genetics Examinations, 1957-58
  - University of Liverpool. Ness Gardens Management Committee. Agenda, 1968
  - University of Liverpool. Proposals for the Establishment of a Medical Research Council Unit of Reproductive Biology, 1971
  - Variation and Heredity
    -See Ser.II, Professor Lewis' Review of Variation and Heredity from 3rd Programme
  - Warfarin Resistance. Bibliography, [1969]
  - Was Darwin Right?, n.d.
- Series III. Research notes, 1911, 1940-1976; 3 boxes, 1.5 lin. feet (Box Series III Boxes 1-3)
  Notes on the following butterflies: Papilio (swallowtail); Biston betularia (the Pepper moth); Heliconius melpomene and H. erato; and Panaxia dominula (the Scarlet Tiger moth). There are also notes on Cepaea nemoralis (the land snail), and the ABO blood groups. In addition, some notebooks contain reading notes summarizing journal articles and the orders of animal classification. Loose notes are arranged by subject; the Latin form of a subject's name has been preferred for use on file folders. Notebooks are arranged by date under the heading "Research Notebook" with undated notebooks grouped after the dated ones. Undated notebooks are arranged alphabetically by subject when discernible. Most of the notebooks contain data on two or more subjects which are noted on the folder when identifiable. Often Sheppard would begin to record data in the first half of a notebook, and subsequently, begin to take notes on a different subject starting from the back of the same notebook.
  The type of data most often recorded is mark, release, and recapture statistics for insects and snails, and breeding or blood line data. Of particular interest is the data collected on Panaxia dominula which spans the years 1941-76 and which was one of Sheppard's central interests. The earliest item is a notebook from 1911, possibly J.R. Hobhouse's, which details some activities in Germany. A record of butterfly captures and pupae purchased, it appears to be additional information on a butterfly collection which Hobhouse donated to the University of Liverpool (see Series I, J.R. Hobhouse). Of interest within the undated notebooks are some notes on the Labour Party in England. Taken immediately after World War II, these notes include questions on the Party's position on the employment of veterans. Other miscellaneous data includes unidentified graphs, and a computer program for statistical work.
  Genetics -- Butterflies, moths; Genetics -- Snails; Human genetics -- Blood groups; Political issues -- England; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.; Zoology -- Classification
  - [Biston betularia], 1956-65; 1972-74
  - Blood Groups, 1951; [1954?-55?]
  - [Cepaea nemoralis], [1940?-50?]; n.d.
  - [Cepaea nemoralis] Brood List, n.d.
  - Gonodontis bidentata Clerck, 1955; 1960
  - Miscellaneous Research Notes, n.d.
  - Panaxia dominula
    - Folder #1, 1941-49
      -See Oversized
    - Folder #2, 1950-51
    - Folder #3, 1952-55
    - Folder #4, 1956-68
  - Panaxia dominula [Death Rates], 1949; 1953
  - [Papilio data], 1954-56; n.d.
  - Research Notebooks
    - #1 -- Misc. Notes, Calendar, 1911; Hobhouse, John Richard, 1893-1961
      Hobhouse, John R.
      Genetics -- Butterflies, moths; Unpublished manuscripts, notes, etc.
    - #2 -- Panaxia dominula, Blood Groups, 1941-53
    - #3 -- Panaxia dominula, Cepaea nemoralis, 1947-52
    - #4 -- Panaxia dominula, 1947-53
    - #5 -- Panaxia dominula, [Reading Notes], 1948?
    - #6 -- [Egg Laying], 1949-50
    - #7 -- Panaxia dominula, Primates, and British Fauna, 1951
    - #8 -- Panaxia dominula, Animal Classification, 1951-52
    - #9 -- Panaxia dominula, Papilio, 1951-52
    - #10 -- Panaxia dominula, 1952
    - #11 -- Papilio, Polymorphism and Population Studies [outline], [1952?]
    - #12 -- Panaxia dominula, Cepaea nemoralis, Papilio machaon, 1952-53
    - #13 -- Cepaea nemoralis, Panaxia dominula, 1953; 1959
    - #14 -- Panaxia dominula #1, 1953
    - #15 -- Panaxia dominula #2, 1953
    - #16 -- Panaxia dominula #3, 1953
    - #17 -- Swallowtail matings (Papilio), [Cepaea nemoralis?], 1953-54
    - #18 -- Panaxia dominula, 1954
    - #19 -- Panaxia dominula, 1954-55
    - #20 -- Populations data, 1955
    - #21 -- Panaxia dominula, Blood Groups, Cepaea nemoralis, 1956
    - #22 -- Cepaea nemoralis, 1956
    - #23 -- Panaxia dominula, 1956
    - #24 -- [Papilio?] hippocoonides, shorthand letters, [1958]
    - #25 -- Moth data, [Panaxia dominula?], 1958-64
    - #26 -- Panaxia dominula, 1959
      -See Ser.III, Research Notebook #13
    - #27 -- Panaxia dominula, [Heliconius?], [Papilio?], 1960
    - #28 -- Panaxia dominula, Biston betularia, 1961-66
    - #29 -- Heliconius erato, Heliconius mel[pomene], 1962
    - #30, 1962-63
    - #31, 1963?
    - #32, 1964-65
    - #33 -- Biston betularia, 1965
    - #34, 1965
    - #35 -- Biston betularia, Panaxia dominula, 1967; 1973; 1976
    - #36 -- Biston betularia, 1968
    - #37 -- Biston betularia, 1968-69
    - #38 -- [Copper Experiments], 1969
    - #39 -- Panaxia dominula, Biston betularia, 1970
    - #40 -- Biston betularia, 1973
      -See Ser.III, Research Notebook #35
    - #41 -- Biston betularia, Panaxia dominula, 1976
    - #42 -- Brachiopods, n.d.
    - #43 -- Cepaea nemoralis, [British Labour Party after WWII], n.d.
    - #44 -- [Computer Program], n.d.
    - #45 -- [Computer Program], n.d.
    - #46 -- [Computer Program], n.d.
    - #47 -- [Graphs], n.d.
    - #48 -- [Graphs], n.d.
    - #49 -- [Graphs (Papilio memnon?)], n.d.
    - #50 -- Panaxia dominula, n.d.
      Bone, Quentin
    - #51 -- [Statistics, Animal Classification], n.d.
    - #52, n.d.
    - #53, n.d.